Your PMI exam there are two terms you need to be familiar with the project management lifecycle and
the project lifecycle the project management lifecycle describes the initiation the planning the executing
monitoring controlling and closing.
It's the common process groups that we all use this project managers the project lifecycle though is
unique to each type of project.
So it describes the phases of the project.
So if you think about in construction that we have the pre-build phase the permits and the surveys and
all the paperwork's the and so on that we have the foundation phase in framing and electrical and plumbing
and finishing that each Beys makes up that project lifecycle the project management lifecycle is always
initiating planning executing monitor controlling and closing.
So we talked about application areas a moment ago the project lifecycle is unique to the type of work
you're doing.
In other words we won't have the same project lifecycle in a manufacturing project as an I.T. project
as a construction project that those are unique to that application area to the type of work that's
being done.
In fact some projects may have their own unique lifecycle as well their own unique phases.
So you might not always have a framing phase or a plumbing phase or whatever the case may be on a construction
project because maybe you are framing your remodeling or doing a drywall or whatever the case may be
in your construction project.
The point I'm trying to make is that the project lifecycle is always unique.
Each phase describes the work and the deliverable that that phase is creating.
So if we have a phase called Foundation we all can relate to well that's creating the foundation in
this phase or if we have a phase called framing we're talking about the skeleton of the house the framing
the structure.
So it's just a quick way of describing what type of work takes place in that phase.
And then at the end of that phase creates that deliverable.
So we're going to see this concept of phases a lot that the end of one phase allows the next phase to
begin and the end of a phase often creates a milestone.
So a milestone is a significant accomplishment in the project.
So the end of the foundation phase would create a milestone of the foundation.
So it describes what works taking place and what does it create.
All right so that's the project lifecycle.
All right.
Good job.
Keep moving forward.